Elizabeth Downe Norris Papers, 1870s-2003
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Elizabeth Norris papers
1870s-2003
Norris, Elizabeth Downe, 1914-2003
MS 508
6 boxes (2.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
YWCA Archivist, Librarian. Papers consist of biographical and family history information, family photographs, writings, and samples from her collections of memorabilia with associated reference files. The bulk of the papers is photographs and materials related to Norris' memorabilia collections.
Elizabeth Downe was born on April 25, 1914 in White Plains, New York, to Albro Farwell and Alice Morse Downe. The family lived in White Plains, New York; Gardner, Massachusetts; and New Haven, Connecticut, where her father worked as a salesman for the American Radiator Company. After graduation from New Haven High School, Downe attended Smith College where she majored in English and religious studies.
After earning her A.B. in 1936, Downe returned home and enrolled in Yale Divinity School. Though financial problems delayed completion of the degree, she received a B.D. in religious education in 1939. (YDS would not award masters degrees to women at that time.) Interested in a career in "religious direction and education," during her Yale years Downe served as Director of the Daily Vacation Bible Schools run by the New Hampshire Council of Congregational Churches in the summer of 1937, and as assistant to the Girl Reserve Secretary of the New Haven YWCA (October 1938-June 1939).
After finishing at Yale, she attended the YWCA's intensive one month Training Institute for Professional Workers at Oberlin College in the summer of 1939. In September of that year Downe took a job as Teen-age Director at the YWCA in Passaic, New Jersey. She returned to the New Haven YWCA in November 1940 as Assistant Residence Director.
In August 1942 she married Roy Edwin Norris and the couple moved to Brooklyn, New York. Roy Norris was then a student at Columbia University and Elizabeth started work as a teller in the Brooklyn Trust Company in December 1942. Unhappy with the work, ("[I] have not found it at all stimulating"), she attempted to find jobs in "social group work" and ended up resigning from the bank in July of 1944.
Elizabeth gave birth to her only child, a son, Donald Edwin Norris, on December 30, 1944.
When she was ready to return to work, she found that her chosen profession required irregular hours, including "a great deal of evening work" that would "now be impossible because of my three year old child." In August of 1948, she began working for the YWCA of the City of New York Central Branch, doing intake interviewing and some public relations. She also did some freelance "membership interpretation" writing for the YWCA of the U.S.A.
Though they remained lifelong friends, beginning in September of 1950 Elizabeth and her husband Roy lived apart, but they did not complete a legal separation agreement until December 1974.
In 1953 Elizabeth enrolled in Columbia University School of Library Science and went to work at the Queensboro Public Library in Jamaica, New York. After earning an M.L.S. in 1955, she worked as Religious Education Librarian at the Union Theological Seminary Library (1955-57) and Librarian at the National Conference of Christians and Jews (1957-63) before returning to the YWCA in June of 1963 as Librarian for the National Association.
Through the many years Norris worked for the National Association, the Library was closely associated with staff doing research, public relations, and maintaining the central filing system. Part of Norris's duties included cataloging and care of a large collection of YWCA publications. Because of her interest and experience with "interpretation" of the Association, Norris regularly wrote on historical and research topics for the YWCA magazine and for brochures and training materials.
At least as early as the 1970s, Norris began to collect memorabilia and ephemera related to women's history, sewing, and a variety of other topics. She became active in postcard clubs and contributed several articles to Postcard Collector magazine. Norris sold much of her collection after the year 2000.
Spurred by the U.S. Bicentennial and the growing interest in women's history, the YWCA of the U.S.A. embarked on an Archives Project in 1976. Elizabeth Norris was appointed Director of the National Endowment for the Humanities-funded project and given responsibility for establishing a permanent "study center" within the Library and providing ongoing scholarly access to the historical records of the Association once the grant-funded Project Archivists had completed surveys and inventories of the records. Following completion of the two-year project late in 1978, "YWCA Historian" was added to Elizabeth Norris's position title to reflect her new role.
Norris developed a regular feature in the YWCA Interchange, called "Archives Box" where she presented historical pieces on a variety of topics. She also produced a number of YWCA history handouts for use in staff and volunteer training. Norris and historian Nancy Marie Robertson collaborated on a chapter about sources and strategies for doing historical research on the YWCA for the book Men and Women Adrift: The YMCA and the YWCA in the City (1997).
Roy Norris died in September 1984 and Elizabeth and Roy's son Donald died October 16th, 1994.
Under severe budget constraints, the YWCA of the USA closed its Archives in September 1992. As part of overall fund-raising effort and in celebration of the 135th anniversary of the founding of the first YWCA in the U.S., the National Association obtained grants to mount an exhibit of historical materials selected from the Archives and contributed by Community Associations. Norris served as Project Manager for this exhibition and accompanying catalogue, "Women First for 135 Years, 1855-1993." With special funding, Elizabeth Norris continued as Librarian and YWCA Historian half-time, later Librarian/Archivist until 1999 as her health permitted.
Elizabeth Norris died on December 24, 2003.
The Elizabeth Downe Norris Papers consist of 2.25 linear ft. of biographical and family history information, photographs, writings, and samples from her collections of memorabilia with associated reference files. The bulk of the papers is photographs and materials related to Norris' memorabilia collections.
This collection is organized into four series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND CORRESPONDENCE contains general biographical information and memorabilia related to Elizabeth Norris, her husband, Roy Edwin Norris, and their son, Donald Edwin Norris. There is also a small genealogical research file and a small amount of correspondence.
II. PHOTOGRAPHS contains photographic prints and a few negatives. They are primarily family group and individual photographs, which document Downe family life in the 1910s and 20s, and the early years of Norris's marriage. Many of the photographs were assembled for Norris's self published family history "The Downe Family: Reflections on Three Generations, 1829-1935."
III. WRITINGS contains a variety of published and unpublished short pieces which give a good sense of Norris' talents as a writer. Subjects are primarily Downe family history, the YWCA, and memorabilia and collecting.
IV. MEMORABILIA COLLECTIONS contains reference materials and selections from Norris's decades of collecting memorabilia. Included are advertising, buttons, cloth patches, a few fabric items, pencils, photographs, pins, postcards, stamps and stickers. Norris's main collecting interests were sewing and needlework, women, and political movements associated with women, such as Temperance and Suffrage. The reference files consist of clippings from major newspapers and magazines and from collectors' publications from the 1970s-90s. Though Norris sold much of her memorabilia collection beginning in 2000, a sampling of the types of items that interested her remains. They are arranged by subject or type of item.
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
The papers were a bequest of Elizabeth Downe Norris and came to the Sophia Smith Collection via Norris's niece and executor, Margery Brady in 2004.
Collectors and collecting--United States; Sewing--History--Sources; Women--United States--History--Sources; Downe family; Norris, Elizabeth, 1914-2003; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.--Employees; Norris, Roy Edwin, d. 1984; Norris, Donald Edwin, 1944-1994
Related materials, including portions of Norris's collection of YWCA postcards, can be found in the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Additional materials are in the Smith College Archives.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND CORRESPONDENCE
  - General 1914-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Education: Yale Divinity School 1993-96, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Marriage 1942-74 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Family
    - Norris, Roy Edwin [spouse] 1929-99 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Norris, Donald Edwin [son] 1944-94 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Genealogical research 1910-89, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence 1947-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- SERIES II. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Norris, Elizabeth Downe 1910s-90s (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Norris, Roy Edwin 1908-70s, undated (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Norris, Donald Edwin 1940s-80s (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Norris groups 1942-98 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Norris album 1941-46 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Downe Family
    - General and miscellaneous 1880s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - Groups 1910s-20s (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Album 1914-21 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Downe, Alice Elizabeth Morse 1870s-1920s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Farwell family 1929, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Conant and Spear families 1918, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gardner, Massachusetts 1907-52, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS
  - General 1936-93 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Family history
    - Miscellaneous short pieces and drafts 1936-79, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "The Downe Family: Reflections on Three Generations,1829-1935" 1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - YWCA 1950-97, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Collecting/postcards 1984-93 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- SERIES IV. MEMORABILIA COLLECTIONS
  - African-American 1980-95, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bookmarks 1969-93, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Book platesundated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Cloth patches, women themes 1970s-80s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Clothing and shoes 1980-92, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Dolls
    - Reference materials 1978-97, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Imagesundated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Expositions, World's Fairs 1892-1965 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Expositions, World's Fairs reference material and correspondence 1970-89, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous 1906-87, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sewing and needlework
    - General 1877-1994, undated (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
    - Women sewing flags/Betsy Ross 1971-95, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Clark's O.N.T. ["Our New Thread"] 1888-1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Instructions 1898-1908, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Postcards 1905-57, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Postcard reference materials 1982-97, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Women sewing 1908-71 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - YWCA [duplicates of photos in YWCA of the U.S.A. Records] 1958-68, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Stamps and stickers with women undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Suffrage 1909-15, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Suffrage reference materials 1980-94, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Temperance 1910-11, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Women
    - General 1911-40, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Reference materials 1977-97, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Three-dimensional items with suffrage/equal rights/women themes: buttons, pencils, stirrers, pins, rubber stamp, felt sash, playing cards, desk calendars (Box 5)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND CORRESPONDENCE
    - Diplomas and certificates:
      - Roy Edwin Norris: Admission to the Junior High Schools, Atlanta, GA, 1927; Booker T. Washington Junior High School, Atlanta, GA, 1930; Morehouse College, 1937; Columbia University, Ph.D., 1971; Morehouse College Alumni Association 40 Year Anniversary Honor Certificate, 1977; Member, Task Force on the Recreation Problems of the Handicapped, n.d. (Box 6)
      - Donald Edwin Norris: Columbia University, BA 1971 (Box 6)
  - SERIES IV. MEMORABILIA COLLECTIONS
    - Drummer Boy needlework pieceundated (Box 6)
    - "Women fought for the vote. Let's make the vote count" poster, Woman's Division of Christian Service, Board of Missions, The Methodist ChurchAug 1956 (Box 6)